Let the magic begin.
Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone is a adventure,
fantasy film directed by Chris Columbus.
Harry Potter has lived under the stairs at his aunt
and uncle's house his whole life.
But on his 11th birthday, he learns he's a powerful wizard—with a place
waiting for him at the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry.
As he learns to harness his newfound powers with the help of the school's kindly headmaster, Harry
uncovers the truth about his parents' deaths—and about the villain who's to blame.
Harry Potter, played by Daniel Radcliffe.
Ron Weasley, played by Rupert Grint.
Hermione Granger, played by Emma Watson.
Albus Dumbledore, played by Richard Harris.
Draco Malfoy, played by Tom Felton.
Severus Snape, played by Alan Rickman.
Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone (also known as Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone in the United States, India, and the
Philippines) is a 2001 fantasy film directed by Chris Columbus and written by Steve Kloves, based on the 1997 novel by J.
It is the first instalment in the Harry Potter film series, and stars Daniel Radcliffe as Harry
Potter, with Rupert Grint as Ron Weasley, and Emma Watson as Hermione Granger.
Its story follows Harry's first year at Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry as he
discovers that he is a famous wizard and begins his formal wizarding education.
Warner Bros.
Pictures bought the film rights to the book in 1999 for
a reported £1 million ($1.65 million).
Production began in the United Kingdom in 2000, with Columbus being chosen to helm the film
from a short list of directors that included Steven Spielberg and Rob Reiner.
Rowling insisted that the entire cast be British and Irish, with the three
leads chosen in August 2000 following open casting calls.
Filming took place at Leavesden Film Studios and historic buildings
around the United Kingdom from September 2000 to March 2001.
Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone premiered at Odeon Leicester Square in London on 4 November
2001 and was released on 16 November in the United Kingdom and the United States.
It became a critical and commercial success, grossing $974 million at the box office during its
initial run and over $1 billion with subsequent re-releases, against a $125 million budget.
It became the highest-grossing film of 2001 and the
second-highest-grossing film at the time.
The film was nominated for several awards, including Academy Awards for Best
Original Score, Best Art Direction and Best Costume Design.
It was followed by seven sequels, beginning with Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets in
2002 and ending with Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2 in 2011.
The film explores themes of witch, school friend,
friendship, london, england, based on novel or book.
The tone is lighthearted.